Guide to the Filippo Tommaso Marinetti Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings by Filippo Tommaso Marinetti, 1895-1944; Series IV; 11.5; (28 boxes)
  - WRITINGS
    - "Sintesi Radiofoniche di F. T. Marinetti"
      - Printed version, Autori e Scrittori, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 1600)
    - Soir abstrait d'aviateur
      - Autograph manuscript poem signed at bottom of the last page. With a few corrections. On verso of the final page: "Aeropoesie soir abstrait". 19 p., numbered [1]-19. (Box 35, Folder 1601)
    - Le soir écrase (éclopé).
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with many corrections Possibly c. 1900. 3 p., including title-page (Box 35, Folder 1602)
    - Soir 1900.
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections. 3 p. (Box 35, Folder 1603)
    - Soldatura
      - Autograph manuscript, the last two pages of which are crossed out. A newspaper clipping glued to center of p. 5. 6 p. (Box 35, Folder 1604)
    - Le soleil enchaîne, roman africain
      See: Box 27, folders 1384-86
    - Sonnet
      - Autograph manuscript poem signed and dated Milano, 10 Dec 1896. 1 p. (Box 35, Folder 1605)
        See also: Box 31, folders 1471-1490; Box 31, folder 1490
    - Sopra Stambul
      - Autograph manuscript poem (?) with corrections Title on verso of last page. 10 p., numbered 1-10. (Box 35, Folder 1606)
    - Spagna Veloce, Contro il vento burbero comandante delle forze del passato
      - Autograph manuscript essay with no corrections 36 p., numbered 1-36. (Box 35, Folder 1607)
    - Spasmes noirs
      - Autograph manuscript poem signed at the bottom of p. 2. 2 p. (Box 35, Folder 1608)
    - [Speeches]
      - Carbon typescript with a pencil sketch of Corsica, labelled in FTM's hand. At the top of p. 1: "Terza serata di poesia, Corsica, Isola Azzurra". 4 p., numbered [1]-4. (Box 36, Folder 1609)
    - [Speeches]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a speech addressed to students in Paris. In French and Italian. 2 p. (Box 36, Folder 1610)
    - [Speeches]
      - Autograph manuscript notes, possibly a preface to a speech given in Venice as FTM praises Dottor Nino Barbantini, Director of the Galleria Internazionale d'Arte Moderna in Palazzo Pesaro, Venice. 4 p., numbered 1-4. (Box 36, Folder 1611)
    - [Speeches]
      - Autograph manuscript fragment of a speech, labelled in blue pencil at the top of p. 1: "Preambolo Seconda Serata Venezia". 9 p. (Box 36, Folder 1612)
    - [Speeches]
      - Autograph manuscript draft of a speech, with corrections, in which FTM refers to the second and third serate in Milan and Turin (p. 1), the Neapolitan public (p. 2 ff.), and the "Manifesto del futurismo, pubblicato un anno fa dal Figaro [20 Feb 1909]" (p. 27). Incomplete, missing final page(s). Apparently an earlier version of IV.29.22. In Italian. 35 p., numbered [1]-31. (Box 36, Folder 1613)
    - [Speeches]
      - Autograph manuscript draft of a speech, apparently a later copy of IV.29.21, but this version is com- plete. In Italian. 41 p., numbered [1]-41. (Box 36, Folder 1614)
    - [Speeches]
      - Autograph manuscript draft of a speech, with many corrections. The text is untitled and unlabelled, but refers to the "manifesto tecnico" on page 1. In Italian. 30 p. numbered 1-33, missing pp. 22, 23, and 25 (Box 36, Folder 1615)
    - Speeches
      See: Box 25, folder 1326
    - Spiralando sopra il transatlantico
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with title on verso of the last page. Originally entitled Spiralando sul Biancamano. 21 p., numbered 1-21. (Box 36, Folder 1616)
        See also: Box 18, folders 1156-72 and Box 36, folder 1617
    - Spiralando sul Biancamano
      - Typescript with corrections, possibly an earlier version of IV.30.1. 2 p., numbered 63-64. (Box 36, Folder 1617)
    - [Lo splendore geometrico e meccanico e la sensibilità numerica]
      - Typescript fragment of the French version with two chapter headings in FTM's hand: "Une poésie aux splendeurs geometriques et mecaniques" and "La poésie simultanée des tables synoptiques". On the verso of page 31 in orange and blue pencil (FTM's hand): "Articoli poemi pubblicati". 7 p., numbered 27-33. (Box 36, Folder 1618)
    - [Stile Futurista] (periodical)
      - Autograph manuscript draft for a letter about Farfa and others, as well as notes for an exhibition review, possibly for the periodical Stile Futurista. 2 p. (Box 36, Folder 1619)
    - Strade e piazze Milanesi nell'Aprile 1919.
      - Manuscript, possibly in the hand of BCM, with corrections in the hand of FTM. The last 5 pages are typescript, and several typescript paragraphs and sections of pages have been integrated into the manuscript portion. The title appears on the verso of page 12, in FTM's hand. 14 p., numbered 1-14 (Box 36, Folder 1620)
        See also: Box 33, folder 1507 and Box 38, folder 1674
    - Su Adrianopoli
      - Manuscript poem, possibly in FTM's hand. Signed at bottom of the last page "Filippo Tommaso Marinetti" Title appears on the verso of the last page along with a list of names crossed out by the author. 6 p., numbered 1-6. (Box 36, Folder 1621)
    - Su Roma, con Benedetta
      - Autograph manuscript fragment, with corrections 2 p. numbered 91-92. (Box 36, Folder 1622)
    - Sua Allegrezza
      - Autograph manuscript dialogue with title at the top of page 1. On verso of last page: "Misurazione" 3 p. (Box 36, Folder 1623)
    - Successivement
      - Autograph manuscript poem. 1 p. (Box 36, Folder 1624)
      - Autograph manuscript poem, same text as IV.30.9, but possibly an earlier version. 3 p., numbered 1-3. (Box 36, Folder 1625)
      - Manuscript poem, possibly in FTM's hand. Same text as IV.30.9 and 10, same format as IV.30.9. 1 p. (Box 36, Folder 1626)
    - Il suggeritore nudo, simultaneità futurista in 11 sintesi
      - Autograph manuscript play(s) with corrections Signed at top of page 1. 114 p., including title- page, numbered 2-99. Enclosed in red folder (Box 36, Folder 1627)
        See also: Box 36, folder 1628
    - [Il suggeritore nudo]
      - Autograph manuscript draft of play, a continuation of IV.30.12 although not enclosed within original grouping. Heavily corrected. 5 p., numbered 100-104. (Box 36, Folder 1628)
    - Sulla Donna
      - Autograph manuscript poem, the first three pages of which may not be in FTM's hand. Signed at the bottom of page 4 by FTM, title at top of page 1, in same hand. 4 p. (Box 36, Folder 1629)
    - Sur Milan
      - Autograph manuscript poem. On verso of last page: "Aeropoesie sur Milan". 16 p., numbered 1-16. (Box 36, Folder 1630)
    - [Tactilism]
      - Proofs of various poems on tactilism: navigazione tattile, ritratto olfattivo di una donna, macchina lirica, temperature del corpo del nuotatore, paesaggio d'odori del mio cane-lupo, Bombardamento di Adrianopoli, and Si, si, cosi, l'aurora sul mare. All are parole in libertà. A fragment from a collection of FTM's poetry 12 p., numbered 279-290. (Box 36, Folder 1631)
        See also: Box 28, folder 1397; Box 30, folder 1451; Box 37, folder 1643
    - Le tambour de feu...
      - Autograph manuscript play with no corrections. A later version of IV.31.2 performed in 1922 in various cities in Italy and in Prague. 188 p., including title-page, numbered 1-190. Missing pages 71-73. (Box 36, Folder 1632)
      - Manuscript play in the hand of BCM, with corrections in the hands of BCM and FTM. An earlier version of IV.31.1. 193 p., numbered 1-195, missing p. 107-108, 159. (Box 36, Folder 1633)
      - Carbon typescript with a few corrections, mostly typing errors. Bound in orange paper. Text corresponds to IV.31.1. 84 p., numbered [1]-84. (Box 36, Folder 1634)
      - Carbon typescript, corresponding to IV.31.3. Bound in blue paper. 84 p., numbered [1]-84. (Box 36, Folder 1635)
      - Carbon typescript, corresponding to IV.31.3 and 4. Bound in orange paper. 84 p., numbered [1]-84. (Box 36, Folder 1636)
      - Carbon typescript of another version of the play A few corrections, mostly typing errors. Bound in orange paper. Text and corrections correspond to other typescript versions. 88 p., numbered [1]-88. (Box 36, Folder 1637)
    - Taxi lune ou claire de lune mécanisé.
      - Autograph manuscript with corrections. 17 p., numbered 1-16. (Box 37, Folder 1638)
        See also: Box 27, folder 1381
    - "Il teatro aereo radiotelevision: Manifesto futurista a Italo Balbo"
      - Printed version, in unidentified newspaper, n.d (Box 37, Folder 1639)
    - Il Teatro Futurista sintetico
      - A combination of newspaper clippings pasted on paper and autograph manuscript additions to this manifesto. Signed on the last page by FTM and Emilio Settimelli. 8 p., numbered 1-8. (Box 37, Folder 1640)
        See also: Box 36, folder 1641; Box 28, folders 1389-1399; Box 37, folder 1649
      - A combination of newspaper clippings and autograph manuscript additions, same as IV.32.2 except signed twice by both FTM and Settimelli on last page (one set of signatures crossed out) and dated 15 Jan 1915. 8 p., numbered 1-8. (Box 37, Folder 1641)
    - Il Teatro totale - sua architettura
      - Autograph manuscript manifesto on the theater, beginning with 12 pages of drawings and diagrams Title on page 1 of text. With many corrections 39 p., 12 pages of drawings, 27 p. of text, the latter numbered 1-26. (Box 37, Folder 1642)
    - Temperature del corpo del nuotatore
      - Autograph manuscript poem, signed at the bottom of the last page. 7 p., numbered 1-7. (Box 37, Folder 1643)
        See also: Box 36, folder 1631; Box 37, folder 1644; Box 30, folder 1451
    - Températures du corps d'un nageur (poésie thermomé- trique mots en liberté).
      - Autograph manuscript poem with corrections. French version of IV.32.5, but with some changes to the text. Signed at the bottom of the last page. 6 p., numbered [1]-6 and also 262-267. (Box 37, Folder 1644)
    - La tempête
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections. The title at the top of every page. 13 p. (Box 37, Folder 1645)
    - Teoria dell'immediato contro le sfumature, Manifesto di Beny
      - Autograph manuscript outline for a manifesto. With corrections. 8 p., numbered [1]-7. (Box 37, Folder 1646)
        See also: Box 37, folders 1654-55
    - "Testamento letterato di G. D'Annunzio"
      - Printed version (title is written in pencil over printed title: "Il saluto del Sindacato fascista Autori Scrittori e degli Aeropoeti futuristi a Gabriele D'Annunzio"), Autori e Scrittori, 1938 Mar (Box 37, Folder 1647)
    - [Theater]
      - Autograph manuscript notes about futurist theater 4 p. (Box 37, Folder 1648)
    - Le Théâtre futuriste synthétique
      - Proofs (?) of an essay by FTM, Emilio Settimelli, and Bruno Corra. Mounted on paper with a few corrections. Published 11 May 1919. 4 p., numbered 1-4. (Box 37, Folder 1649)
        See also: Box 37, folder 1640
    - Théâtre synthétique futuriste
      - Manuscript "synthéses théâtrales" by FTM, Balla, Boccioni, Bruno, Buzzi, Cangiullo, Cantarelli, Carli, Cerati, Chiti, Cini, Corra, D'Alba, Della Pergola, Depero, Dessy, Di Leone, Diobelli, Folgore, Ginna, Jannelli, Mara, Nannetti, Pratella, Refecchi, Settinielli, Quinterio, Trilluci, Volt. All in the hand of FTM, with corrections 165 p., each contribution numbered separately (Box 37, Folder 1650)
    - [Thesaurus]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a thesaurus corres- ponding futurist words to traditional vocabulary In French. 36 p. (Box 37, Folder 1651)
    - [Thesaurus]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a type of thesaurus, with some notes on colors. In Italian and French 83 p. (Box 37, Folder 1652)
    - [Trains]
      - Autograph manuscript notes about train imagery. 1 p. (Box 37, Folder 1653)
    - [Treatises]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a treatise on pleasure(s). In Italian; more complete than French version. 11 p., numbered 1-9, preceded by a 2-page outline (Box 37, Folder 1654)
        See also: Box 37, folder 1654 and Box 37, folder 1646
    - [Treatises]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a treatise on pleasure(s). With corrections. In French. 27 p., numbered 1-3 (outline), and 1-23 (Box 37, Folder 1655)
        See also: Box 37, folder 1646 and Box 37, folder 1648
    - Le tremplin
      - Autograph manuscript poem with corrections, signed and dated on page 2, Vetriolo, 15 Jul 1897. 2 p. (Box 37, Folder 1656)
        See also: Box 37, folder 1490
    - Trincee di bambini
      - Typescript scenario with no corrections. 3 p., numbered [1]-3. (Box 37, Folder 1657)
        See also: Box 37, folder 1658
      - Autograph manuscript with many corrections, signed at the bottom of the last page, and on verso of last page. 15 p., numbered 1-15. (Box 37, Folder 1658)
    - [Tunisian War]
      - Autograph manuscript miscellaneous notes on cut-out photographs of northern Africa from magazines. 3 p. (Box 37, Folder 1659)
    - Varie Velocità dal mio amoroso possesso di Rio di Janeiro
      - Autograph manuscript essay with corrections Consists of eight untitled sections. Possibly from 1926 (FTM's trip to Rio, etc.). 70 p., numbered 1-36 and 1-27. (Box 37, Folder 1660)
    - La variété des noirs
      - Autograph manuscript essay, with a few corrections 20 p. (Box 37, Folder 1661)
    - Velocità.
      - Autograph manuscript notes for a manifesto, with corrections. 9 p. (Box 37, Folder 1662)
        See also: Box 28, folders 1389-99
      - Autograph manuscript with corrections, signature and title appear at the bottom of the last page. 8 p. includes scrap entitled: "L'aviazione, la Poesia e le Arte" (Box 37, Folder 1663)
    - Velocità, film
      - Autograph manuscript narrative for a film. With a few corrections. Signed on last page. 59 p., incl cover title; numbered 1-8, [11]-48. (Box 37, Folder 1664)
    - Velocità Brasiliane
      - Autograph manuscript, with a few corrections, signed on the last page. 17 p., numbered 1-16. (Box 37, Folder 1665)
    - Venezianella e studentaccio
      - Typescript with no corrections, consisting of 19 unnumbered sections. In a heavy orange folder with title and FTM's name written on cover in BCM's hand 118 p., numbered [1]-118. (Box 37, Folder 1666)
      - Carbon typescript of 19 unnumbered sections. With no corrections. Corresponds to IV.33.7. In an off- white folder. 118 p., numbered [1]-118 (Box 37, Folder 1667)
      - Carbon typescript of another version of IV.33.7-8. Also consists of 19 unnumbered sections. In blue folder with title on cover in BCM's hand. 126 p., numbered [1]-125. (Box 37, Folder 1668)
    - [Venice]
      - Autograph manuscript notes in Italian and newspaper clippings about Venice, including many pages about San Marco. Heavily corrected. Enclosed is a 1-page outline of notes by LMB. 49 p., including 4 pages of newspaper clipping, 1 postcard, and 44 p. of text (Box 38, Folder 1669)
        See also: Box 36, folder 1610
      - Autograph manuscript notes in French, with corrections Title [Venise] appears on verso of last page. 4 p. (Box 38, Folder 1670)
      - Autograph manuscript draft of an essay in French, with corrections, and other notes, some referring to Poesia. 20 p., numbered 2-8, missing page 1. (Box 38, Folder 1671)
      - Autograph manuscript fragment of a poem, with "La lune ivre et les lagunes(?)" written on verso of the last page with other notes. 6 p., numbered 5-10. (Box 38, Folder 1672)
    - [Vertenza Pirazzoli-Belli]
      - Autograph manuscript in the hand of FTM and others, about the trial between Pirazzoli and Belli. 6 p. (Box 38, Folder 1673)
        See also: Box 26, folder 1362; Series V, Box 46, folder 1793; Series III, Box 7, folder 153
    - [Via Mercanti, the battle of, 15 Apr 1919]
      - Untitled typescript carbon, corrected, beginning: "L'ardito Maraviglia ci teneva costantemente informati dei movimenti rossi." 3 p., numbered [1]-3. (Box 38, Folder 1674)
        See also: Box 33, folder 1508 and Box 36, folder 1620
    - La ville charnelle (published in 1908)
      - Proofs without corrections. Incomplete. 158 p., numbered [1]-227. (Box 38, Folder 1675)
      - Proofs with various typefaces pasted on larger sheets of paper. Incomplete. With headings and some additions in the hand of FTM. 62 p. (Box 38, Folder 1676)
      - Proofs without corrections. Incomplete. 131p., numbered (70)-229 (Box 38, Folder 1677)
      - Proofs with corrections. Incomplete. An earlier version than IV.35.1 and 3. 74 p., numbered (70)-167 (Box 38, Folder 1678)
      - Proofs with some corrections. Same version as IV.36.4, with fewer corrections. 157 p., numbered 1-189, probably most pages missing are blank, except for pp. 52-57 (Box 38, Folder 1679)
      - Autograph manuscript, Italian version, with few corrections. Incomplete; includes only the section "Poeti" 57 p., numbered 186-242 (Box 38, Folder 1680)
    - La ville d'émeraude
      - Autograph manuscript novel (?) with a few cor- rections. Continued in IV.34.9. 181 p., including title-page. Numbered [1]-180. (Box 39, Folder 1681)
      - Autograph manuscript continuation of IV.34.8. 189 p., numbered 181-370. (Box 39, Folder 1682)
    - La Ville Hantee
      - Autograph manuscript fragment with corrections 3 p., numbered 21 bis - 21 quatre (Box 39, Folder 1683)
    - La Vita dei Motori
      - Autograph manuscript essay about different motors 14 p., including cover title, numbered 1-11. (Box 39, Folder 1684)
    - La Vita dell'Italia Fascista
      - Autograph manuscript essay with corrections Accompanied by a blue folder on which is written the title and "1a stesura" (first draft) (in the hand of BCM). Divided into several untitled sections. Many pages consist of newspaper clippings pasted on paper. 83 p., including blue folder. Various sections numbered separately (Box 39, Folder 1685)
        See also: Box 24, folder 1308
    - Vita dell'Italia Fascista, non La Storia del Fascismo
      - Autograph manuscript essay, with corrections. A later version of IV.36.4. 131 p., numbered 1-131. Pages 101-114 are newsprint and proofs (?) mounted on paper (Box 39, Folder 1686)
    - "La vita e l'opera di Gabriele D'Annunzio: sintezzate da S. E. Marinetti"
      - Printed version, La Giovine Calabria, 1938 Apr 6 (Box 39, Folder 1687)
    - Vita Futuristica di Capri, o Amorosa Capri fuori Tempo-spazio, Avventure sorprendenti le soavi battaglie di Capri futurista
      - Manuscript fragment in the hand of BCM. In a heavy orange folder, labelled with FTM's name and the title of the essay and "a mano scritto da Mammina" (last two words in hand of LMB). 69 p., numbered 1-64. (Box 39, Folder 1688)
      - Carbon typescript with corrections and additions in the hand of BCM. In a heavy orange folder labelled with FTM's name and short title in BCM's hand. 113 p., numbered 1-112. (Box 39, Folder 1689)
      - Typescript with some corrections (probably in BCM's hand). In a yellow folder with FTM's name and title of the essay on the cover, in BCM's hand. Enclosed is a small piece of paper labelled "2a copia" (on the verso, 2 lines of typescript). 112 p., numbered 1-112. (Box 39, Folder 1690)
    - Vita inumana
      - Autograph manuscript outline for a novel. 5 p. (Box 40, Folder 1691)
    - Volando sopra Piazza del Duomo
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with a few corrections, signed on the last page. Title on verso of the last page; at top of page 1, heading reads: "Serie di seconde parti di immagini aviatorie". 7 p., numbered 1-7. (Box 40, Folder 1692)
      - Autograph manuscript poem, possibly a later version of IV.37.5. 9 p., numbered 1-9. (Box 40, Folder 1693)
      - Manuscript in the hand of BCM written in verse form. Signed by FTM on last page. 3 p., numbered 1-3, over which, in pencil, numbered 65-67. (Box 40, Folder 1694)
    - Women and Futurism
      - Typescript translation of FTM's work into English by André Tridon Typed on verso of another typescript, a fragment of an introduction to an unknown work about Marxism and capitalism. 5 p., numbered [1]-5. (Box 40, Folder 1695)
    - [World War I]
      - Autograph manuscript account, in the form of a journal or diary, of Oct 22-27, 1915. With a few corrections. 39 p., numbered 1-32. (Box 40, Folder 1696)
        See also: De Maria, Futurismo e Fascismo, p. 488, for mention of the Futurists' activities during the period concerned in this essay. In Italian
    - [World War I]
      - Autograph manuscript notes and a clipping for a book about World War I, including a 1-page drawing/diagram of FTM and Boccioni. 6 p. (Box 40, Folder 1697)
    - Zang Tumb Tumb
      - Autograph manuscript complete and in order, despite pagination. (First half) First 6 pages are proofs, the rest is manuscript in FTM's hand, with a few corrections. In French. 71 p. some fragments pasted together. Numbered 1-56 bis (Box 40, Folder 1698)
      - Autograph manuscript (Second half) This section begins near the middle of the fifth chapter In French. Some pages are proofs; the whole manu- script with corrections and printing instructions In FTM's hand. 118 p., numbered 57-162. Page 157 includes 2 paragraphs cut from the printed manifesto "L'art des bruits" 1913, Mar 11. (Box 40, Folder 1699)
      - Autograph manuscript preface entitled "La destruction de la syntaxe. L'imagination sans fils Les mots en liberté." Includes most of the printed manifesto "L'imagination sans fils et les mots en liberté" cut up and mounted on paper. Heavily corrected and signed at bottom of last page In French, apparently the French translation of the preface to the 1914 Italian edition of the work Incomplete; title and beginning pages missing Unpublished. 18 p., numbered 1 bis-4 f. Page size varies (Box 40, Folder 1700)
      - Autograph manuscript fragment. See: pp. 112-113 of text. In Italian. 2 p. (Box 40, Folder 1701)
      - Proof of the French version. With corrections Unpublished. 99 p., numbered 21-119. (Box 40, Folder 1702)
        See also: Oversize Box 54, folder 2003
      - "Hadirlik" section. 7h marked in FTM's hand in blue pencil. 21 p. (Box 40, Folder 1703)
      - Publicity broadside, titled "Marinetti in Russia"
  - MISCELLANEOUS AND UNIDENTIFIED NOTES
    - Autograph manuscript notes beginning "Già ho ritornato..." 1 p. (Box 40, Folder 1704)
    - Autograph manuscript notes about art beginning "1474 Michelangelo, 1746 Goya..." 2 p. (Box 40, Folder 1705)
    - Autograph manuscript notes and drawing written on envelope and letter to FTM from a friend (signed "Tua") dated [1916] Dec 10. 6 p., 4 pages on letter plus 2 pages of notes on envelope (Box 40, Folder 1706)
    - Autograph manuscript notes on a postcard with a picture of Villa Ruggi. 2 p. (Box 40, Folder 1707)
    - Autograph manuscript notes for a poem, in French 1 p. (Box 40, Folder 1708)
    - Autograph manuscript notes beginning: "...sabbia del deserto bianco..." 3 p. (Box 40, Folder 1709)
    - Autograph manuscript notes, some mention of "manifesti" and "aeropoeti", at top of second sheet beginning "Le Diabolique". In Italian and French. 3 p. (Box 40, Folder 1710)
    - Autograph manuscript notes for poems. In French Probably ca. 1900. 3 p. (Box 40, Folder 1711)
    - Autograph manuscript notes in French and Italian French page dated at bottom 10 Feb 1898. 2 p. (Box 40, Folder 1712)
    - Autograph manuscript essay in French. Incomplete With many corrections. Beginning: "D'autres groupes..." 5 p. (Box 40, Folder 1713)
    - Autograph manuscript notes, including mention of "aeropoesia". In Italian. 2 p. (Box 40, Folder 1714)
    - Autograph manuscript notes. In Italian. The heading on one page reads: "Gli eccentrici". 2 p. (Box 40, Folder 1715)
    - Autograph manuscript notes beginning: "Il massimo dell'espressione..." 1 p. (Box 40, Folder 1716)
    - Autograph manuscript notes with comments on America and New York. 4 p. (Box 40, Folder 1717)
    - Autograph manuscript notes from a diary, dated Nov/Dec 1927, 4 p. (Box 40, Folder 1718)